BETH: Most people express their
emotions through verbal communication,
or nonverbally through body language
and facial expressions and extreme
emotions can also be shown by
physical actions such as throwing or
punching something to show anger or by
hugging for affection or reassurance.
JOE: This is not as easy for individuals
with autism who often find behaviour
is their main form communication,
whether it's good or bad and it’s
an expression of feelings and needs.
Individuals with autism might
behave in challenging ways because
they have trouble understanding
what's happening around them.
BETH: They may not comprehend what
other people are saying or communicating
non-verbally and they may have difficulty
communicating their own wants and
needs, which can lead to frustration.
A behaviour that may seem unnecessary or
challenging to others, for the individual
with autism is there to get attention,
escape from something, gain access to
something or is automatic or sensory.
JOE: In autism all behaviour has
a functional element and behaviour
that challenges are often described
as communicating unmet needs.
However, there may be a range of
factors that may be associated
with behaviour that challenges.
Behaviour can be considered a
problem if it limits access to
things a person enjoys, interferes
with learning new things, affects
interactions with others or limits a
family from enjoying things together.
BETH: Behaviours that challenge,
often form in childhood due to their
inability to use vocal language
to express their wants and needs.
Children with autism may often struggle
with the word ‘no’ and will wait
for things to be brought to them.
Behaviours that challenge, are
a way of managing frustration
or coping with feelings.
JOE: Behaviours will persist, if
the behaviour itself meets the needs
of the individual or there is some
reinforcement of those behaviours.
It is important to be aware
that behaviours serve a
function for an individual.